Now it would be worthwhile taking a look at
والآن، من المهم أن ننظر إلى
an existing freelancing profile and go over it's key fields.
ملف شخصي لموظف حر وأن نتفقد أجزاءه الرئيسية.
This will help us really understand how a typical profile looks like,
سوف يساعدنا هذا في فهم ما يبدو عليه الشكل الاعتيادي للملف الشخصي فهمًا جيدًا،
and will also deepen our understanding of the kind of content that we can put in here.
كما أنه سوف يعمق من فهمنا لنوع المحتوى الذي يمكننا وضعه فيه.
First field here is name,
الخانة الأولى هنا هي الاسم،
straightforward, not enough room to go round there.
مباشرةً وبدون مساحة كافية للتحرك.
Now, usually many freelancing platforms require
تتطلب العديد من منصات العمل الحر
short bios which appear in not only your profile,
سيرة قصيرة لتظهر ليس فقط على صفحتك الشخصية
but also in different search results when clients are
ولكن أيضًا في نتائج البحث التي تظهر للعملاء عندما
looking for freelancers with specific skills,
يكونوا يبحثون عن موظفين يمتلكون مهارات محددة،
and as we discussed earlier,
وكما قلنا من قبل
it is important for these bios to be short and crisp.
فمن المهم أن تكون هذه السير مقتضبة وبليغة.
Cut to the chase, and get straight to the point.
فكن مختصرًا وادخل في صلب الموضوع مباشرةً.
Remember, our typical plan is skimming not reading a profile end-to-end.
وتذكر أن هدفنا عادةً هو القراءة الموجزة وليس التفصيلية لكل صفحة شخصية من أولها لآخرها.
In this example of the bio that you see,
سوف تلاحظ في هذه السيرة التي تراها هنا كمثال
you will note that the freelancer has clearly pointed out
أن الموظف أشار بوضوح
their core expertise even though their focus areas are more than those.
إلى خبراته الفنية الأساسية رغم أن مجالات التركيز الخاصة به أكبر من ذلك.
This really helps the client to quickly identify what their core strength is.
ويساعد هذا العميل في أن يحدد سريعًا نقاط قوتك الأساسية.
Secondly, specifically calling out what you have done for clients in the past
ثانيًا، الاستشهاد بما فعلته للعملاء في الماضي
using your core strength gives
باستخدام نقاط قوتك الأساسية يعطيك
an additional metric to the client about what you can do for them.
مقياسًا إضافيًا لدى العميل حول ما يمكنك فعله له.
It also demonstrates your subject knowledge,
كما أنه يبرهن على حجم معرفتك بالموضوع
your ability to measure success as
وعلى قدرتك على قياس نجاحك
compared to simply mentioning your scale in the profile.
مقارنة بذكر نطاق عملك فقط على الصفحة.
Third, as we also discussed earlier,
ثالثًا، من الجيد كما قلنا من قبل
it is okay to put in formal details like a book that you
أن تضع تفاصيل رسمية مثل كتاب
provide to clients to start up a conversation with them.
تقدمه للعملاء لتبدأ حوارًا معهم.
Clients, especially new clients,
يحب العملاء خاصة الجدد منهم
like getting into conversations,
أن يجروا المحادثات
warming up before they decide to start spending money.
التمهيدية قبل أن يأخذوا القرار بإنفاق أموالهم.
If they see such offer in your bio,
إذا رأوا مثل هذا العرض في سيرتك
they're more likely to contact you since there's nothing to lose,
فسوف يكون من الأرجح أن يتواصلوا معك بما أنه ليس هناك ما يخسرونه،
and you get a chance to talk to a potential client as well about
وسوف تتاح لك الفرصة أيضًا لأن تتحدث مع العميل المحتمل عن
solutions to their task or a project with the potential of working with them.
حلول مشكلته أو مشروعه مع وجود إمكانية العمل معه.
Now they would most likely be a skill section in a freelancing profile,
غالبًا ما يحتوي ملف الموظف الحر الشخصي على قسم للمهارات
which will require you to list down the skills you have along with short descriptions.
والذي سيتطلب منك أن تكتب قائمة بالمهارات التي تمتلكها مع وصف مختصر لكل منها.
Now, it is again important here to be short and crisp.
ومن المهم هنا أيضًا أن تكون مختصرًا وبليغًا.
Call-out significant aspects of your experience with these skills.
استخدم تلك المهارات لاستدعاء الجوانب المتميزة لخبرتك.
For example, as we saw in the bio,
فمثلًا وكما رأينا في السيرة
quantifying your past success with a specific skill,
لا يُبدي التحديد الكمي لنجاحاتك السابقة مع مهارة ما
not only demonstrates to the client that you can
للعميل قدرتك الفعلية على
actually work using that skill successfully,
استخدام تلك المهارة جيدًا فحسب،
but it also demonstrates your knowledge in the subject and
ولكنه أيضًا يُظهر مدى معرفتك بالموضوع
your ability to express the result quantifiably.
وقدرتك على التعبير عن النتائج بشكل كمي.
You'll also note that when the freelancer does that for another skill in this profile,
سوف تلاحظ أيضًا في هذه الصفحة الشخصية أنه عندما تفعل الموظفة الحرة نفس الشيء مع مهارة أخرى
she also gives the company's name,
فهي تضع اسم الشركة أيضًا
and links to their website.
ورابط موقعها الإلكتروني.
It's a great idea to do that,
إنها فكرة رائعة أن تفعل ذلك،
provided the company does not prohibit to use their name,
بشرط ألا تكون الشركة تحظر استخدام اسمها
and the fact that you have worked for them publicly,
أو ذكر عملك معها علنًا
either in service agreement or a non-disclosure agreement.
سواء عملت لديها باتفاق تقديم خدمات أو باتفاق سرية.
If you're not restricted,
إن لم تكن هناك قيود عليك
it's a great idea to put a name,
فاستخدامك للاسم والرابط فكرة عظيمة
and a link, because that brings much more credibility to your claim.
لأنها تعطي مصداقية أكبر بكثير لادعاءاتك.
Now when you are quantifying the result of an engagement,
أحيانًا عندما تقوم بتحديد نتائج عمل ما تحديدًا كميًا
sometimes it might be important to provide the client with
يغدو من المهم أن تعطي العميل
some benchmark for them to evaluate how significant that contribution was.
معيارًا للقياس حتى يمكنه تقدير أهمية إسهامك لذلك العمل.
Now for example, look at the third skill here,
انظر للمهارة الثالثة هنا على سبيل المثال
conversion rate of 2.7 percent.
والتي تقول أن معدل التحويل يبلغ 2.7 في المائة.
Now that would probably appear pretty low to a client
من الممكن أن يبدو هذا معدلًا منخفضًا بالنسبة لعميل
who does not know much about online ads.
لا يعرف الكثير عن الإعلانات الإلكترونية.
In fact, there's a high probability that the client does not know about conversions,
وفي الحقيقة هناك احتمال كبير أن يكون العميل لا يعرف شيئًا عن التحويلات
which is why they're engaging an expert like you.
وهو لهذا السبب يوظف خبير مثلك.
Now when you give a link in your profile to average conversion rates on Google ads,
لكن إذا وضعت رابطًا على صفحتك الشخصية لمتوسط معدلات التحويلات لإعلانات جوجل
and if the client sees that the average is around 2.1 percent,
ورأى العميل أن المتوسط هو 2.1 في المائة
2.7 starts appearing to be a good conversion rate relatively.
فسوف يبدو له معدل 2.7 كمعدل تحويل جيد بالمقارنة.
You will see that this kind of education to the client might
سترى أنك ربما ستحتاج هذا النوع من إطلاع العميل
be needed even while you are working with the client multiple times,
حتى وإن كنت قد عملت معه مرات عديدة
even without the client asking for it for them to
وحتى إن لم يطلب هو ذلك،
value your contribution in the larger picture for them.
وهذا حتى يمكنه أن يقدر إسهامك للصورة الكبرى بالنسبة له.
The client may not know what they don't know.
فربما لا يعرف العميل مقدار ما يجهله.
Now another important section in a profile is
من الأقسام المهمة الأخرى في الملف الشخصي هو
generally one that talks about your past experiences.
القسم الذي يتحدث بشكل عام عن خبراتك السابقة.
The projects that you've done,
أي المشاريع التي قمت بها
work projects, informal projects.
سواء مشاريع العمل أو المشاريع غير الرسمية.
This section shows what you have done with other clients
يوضح هذا القسم ما فعلته للعملاء الآخرين
in the past and could really help the client in assessing
في الماضي ويمكنه حقًا أن يساعد العميل المحتمل في تقييم
the kind of work that you have done in the past so that
أنواع الأعمال التي قمت بها في السابق حتى يمكنه
they can see if it matches with the work that they have for you.
رؤية ما إذا كانت تتوافق مع العمل الذي يريدك أن تقوم به أو لا.
Again, as we discussed earlier,
وكما قلنا سابقًا
this two needs to be short and crisp.
فإن هذا القسم أيضًا يجب أن يكون مختصرًا وبليغًا.
We don't want to write long paragraphs for each experience or project.
فلا يجب أن تكتب فقرات طويلة عن كل خبرة أو مشروع.
Now one thing to point out here is that it is a really good idea to provide
أحد الأشياء التي يجب التنويه عنها هنا هو أنه من الجيد أن تضع
any links to your projects as long as they're not protected by an NDA.
أي روابط لمشاريعك طالما أنها غير مشمولة باتفاق سرية.
This will give the client direct access to your work and the output of your work.
فسوف يعطي هذا للعميل طريقة مباشرة للوصول لأعمالك ونتائجها.
If you're early in your career and don't have much work experience,
لو أنك في بداية مشوارك المهني وليس لديك خبرات سابقة كبيرة
link to a personal project could really help in
فمن شأن وضعك لرابط مشروع شخصي أن يساعد في إظهار
showing off the kind of work that you can do for the client.
نوع العمل الذي يمكنك تقديمه للعميل.